Finding Aid for Arts of Citizenship Program (University of Michigan) records, 1997-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arts of Citizenship Program (University of Michigan) records 1997-2007
University of Michigan. Arts of Citizenship Program.
07143 Bimu 2
The Arts of Citizenship Program at the University of Michigan fostered the role of the arts and humanities through collaborative cultural partnerships and community projects in the Ann Arbor and Detroit area. The program aimed to enrich public life and to enlarge the university's educational mission. These records contains notes, correspondence, publicity, audiovisual materials, presentations, and other material documenting the administration, public programming, and community partnerships undertaken by the Arts of Citizenship program. Also included is a website capture taken July 18, 2005.
2.75 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor # 9294 ) was received from the unit in July 2005. Digital records were captured through direct transfer on July 18, 2005
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Arts of Citizenship Program was founded in 1998 during the University of Michigan's Year of the Humanities and Arts (YoHA) during the 1997-1998 academic year. YoHA's Arts of Citizenship initiative brought to campus distinguished intellectuals, artists, designers, and cultural advocates, among them Ken Burns and First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton, to discuss their work and the importance of the humanities and arts in general. AOC became a separate unit under the Office of the Vice President for Research in May 1998. Since AOC was founded in 1998, core funding came from the UM Office of the Vice President for Research and from other UM units, including the Whitaker Fund for the Improvement of Teaching. Grants and gifts for specific community projects came from Ford Motor Company, Community Foundation for Southeastern Michigan, Michigan Humanities Council, Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation, McKinley Foundation of Ann Arbor, and Ann Arbor Area Community Foundation. Recognition for Arts of Citizenship projects has included an Award of Merit in Education from the Historical Society of Michigan (2001) and awards from the Michigan Association of Broadcasters (2002) and the Michigan Associated Press (2003).
AOC integrated local projects with national cultural debates and ambitious research with community collaboration across a variety of disciplines in the arts, the humanities, and design. AOC pursued its goals through forming partnerships between the University of Michigan faculty and students with schools, museums, libraries, arts organizations, theater companies, dance troupes, public agencies, and grassroots groups. AOC also developed courses that combined rigorous study with practical community work and provided start-up funding for innovative teaching and creative projects.
One of the most notable projects was "Students on Site" (SOS), the first project launched by AOC in 1998. SOS brought together University of Michigan faculty, archivists, and students with local K-12 teachers. They used the history and landscape of a historic riverfront district as the site for an innovative interdisciplinary, multi-week curriculum for third and fourth grade classrooms in the public schools. AOC developed an online teaching archive of documents about the history of Ann Arbor, created by University of Michigan students for K-12 students. In October 2001, the project won an Award of Merit in Education from the Historical Society of Michigan. SOS became the model for the other AOC projects, of which there were 18 total.
David Scobey served as the director of the program from 1998 until 2005.
Following Scobey's departure the program was refocused a bit, incorporating more projects directed by graduate students. The current website for AOC is at http://www.artsofcitizenship.umich.edu/?page_id=12.
The Arts of Citizenship (AOC) Program documentation consists of notes, correspondence, publicity, audiovisual materials (audiocassettes, CDs, videotapes), and other material documenting the daily administrative activities, public programming, outreach, research, and community partnerships. The record group is divided into three series: Administration, Project Files, and Website. These series represent the original order of materials as received upon accession. The researcher should note that the records do not provide an in-depth portrayal of AOC, but rather information about the operation, functions, and details on specific projects undertaken by the program.
Subjects:
Broadway Bridge (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--History--20th century.; Education--Experimental methods.; Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scobey, David M., 1954-; University of Michigan. Arts of Citizenship Program.; Underground Railroad--Michigan--Detroit.; University of Michigan. Office of the Vice-President for Research.; University of Michigan--Students.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
African Americans--Michigan--Detroit--20th century.; Detroit (Mich.)--History--20th century.; Hallelujah (Choreographic work: Lerman); Lerman, Liz.; Liz Lerman Dance Exchange.; Michigan Central Railroad Depot (Detroit, Mich.)--History.; Public radio--Michigan--Detroit.; Radio programs--Michigan--Detroit.; Riots--Michigan--Detroit--History--20th century.; Scobey, David M., 1954-; University of Michigan. Arts of Citizenship Program.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Audiocassettes.; CD-ROMs.; Compact discs.; Videotapes.; Sound recordings.; Websites.
- Administration
  The Administration series (0.75 linear feet) includes information about awards, letters of support for AOC, budgets, events, committees, course syllabi, presentations, program summaries, project and partnership listings, publicity, reports, and press coverage. Information on individual projects is found in the Project Files series. Committee records feature two groups, the Graduate Working Group and P-SPACE. The P-SPACE Working Group (Public Scholarship, Public Art, Cultural Engagement) included the Arts of Citizenship, Imagining America, and the Scholarly Publications Office of Digital Library Services, who proposed an online publication series dedicated to public cultural projects and public scholarship in the arts, humanities, and design. Course syllabi are taken from five classes: "Community Resources," UC 310, UC 312, UC 313, and Dance 490.
  - Administrative Files
    - Awards 2000-2005 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 2002-2005 (Box 1)
      - Letters of Support 2002-2004 (Box 1)
      - Nomination Application 2002 (Box 1)
    - Budget
      - General 1999-2001 (Box 1)
      - General 2007 (Box 1)
      - Salaries and Proposals 2004-2007 (Box 1)
    - Committees
      - Graduate Working Group 2002-2003 (Box 1)
      - Planning Committee Meeting Notes 2005-2007, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - P-SPACE (Box 1)
    - Conference Planning Materials 2007 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1997-2006 (Box 1)
    - Course Syllabi (Box 1)
    - Presentations, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 1)
      (Includes CD-ROM with PowerPoint presentation)
    - Press Coverage 1999-2004 (Box 1)
    - Program Summaries (Box 1)
    - Project and Partnership Listings 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Publicity (Flyers and Brochures) (Box 1)
    - Reports 1997-2002 (Box 1)
      (Including report on Year of Humanities and Arts by Julie Ellison)
  - Events
    - Citizenship year 2006-2007 (Box 1)
    - Event Coordinator Applications 2006 (Box 1)
    - Global Arts 2006 (Box 1)
    - Winter Conference 2006 (Box 1)
- Project Files
  The Project Files series (2 linear feet) contains 15 subseries comprising individual projects. Files are organized and described by individual project. The richest description of each individual project is located on the captured website. The researcher should note that not all projects listed on the captured website are equally documented or found within these records.
  - "2001 Hastings Street"
    The "2001 Hastings Street" Project (8 folders) includes analog and audio records. The core of the documentation consists of audio cassette tapes of interviews done with senior citizens who lived on Hastings Street in Detroit's "Black Bottom" area in the 1940s. The interviewees and the subjects covered are identifiable through the Post Interview Reports found in this subseries. A play based on excerpts from the oral history interviews was created and performed in conjunction with the Mosaic Youth Theatre of Detroit. Other materials include a description of the final exhibit, an educational packet, a script of the play, press coverage of the play, and designs of an anticipated website.
    - Educational Packet (Box 1)
    - Exhibit Information (Box 1)
    - Post Interview Reports (Box 1)
    - Press Coverage (Box 1)
    - Script (Box 1)
    - Website Design (Box 1)
    - "Y-Gee's Canteen" (Box 1)
    - Audio recordings
      - "Best of Our Knowledge", 1 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      - Interviews, 59 audiocassettes in case (Box 2)
  - Broadway Park Design Project
    The Broadway Park Design Project (4 folders) contains committee records and reports. The project included collaborative work on the reconstruction of Ann Arbor's Broadway bridges. There are two committees included, the Community Advisory Board, which offered a community perspective, and the Broadway Bridge Consulting Team, formed in response to a request by Ann Arbor's mayor to prepare a site plan of opportunities for public art projects and outdoor educational possibilities. Two reports from the project are included, the 2004 Broadway Park Design Project annual report and the 2002 website plan.
    - Committees
      - Community Advisory Board (Agenda and Minutes) 2003 (Box 2)
      - Broadway Bridge Consulting Team (Minutes and Agendas) 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Broadway Park Design Report 2004 (Box 2)
      - Website Design Plan 2002 (Box 2)
  - Children of Abraham
    The Children of Abraham Project (10 folders) contains letters of support, meeting notes, press coverage, budget and grant information, publicity, reflections and thoughts, and scripts. The reflections and thoughts includes two documents, written reflections on the project by David Scobey and Josephine Tsai, analyzing the project's successes and shortcomings.
    - Letters of Support 2004 (Box 2)
    - Budget 2005 (Box 2)
    - Grants 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - Internal Correspondence 2005 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Notes 2004 (Box 2)
    - Press Coverage 2004 (Box 2)
    - Project Evaluations 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - Publicity 2004 (Box 2)
    - Reflections and Thoughts 2004 (Box 2)
    - Scripts 2004 (Box 2)
  - "Detroit Connections" Project
    The "Detroit Connection" Project (2 folders) contains press coverage and a project evaluation from 2003-2004. The press coverage includes articles describing the role of University of Michigan students in the project, while the project evaluation is written by Ceci Mendez, a project coordinator.
    - Press Coverage 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Project Evaluations 2003 (Box 2)
  - "Emerging Voices" Project
    The "Emerging Voices" Project (1 folder) consists of primary source material from the project's implementation, including articles and documentation of oral history interviews.
    - Primary Source Material 2000 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Legacies
    The Environmental Legacies Project (2 folders) includes lesson plans and project summaries. The lesson plans contain a small book created by children that is used to start off the session, as well as actual lesson plans and a report that describes and critiques the project. General summaries of the project and the 1999-2000 pilot implementation summary are found in the project summaries.
    - Lesson Plans 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Project Summaries 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Hallelujah Project
    The Hallelujah Project (4 folders) includes correspondence, photographs, press coverage, and videocassettes. Correspondence covers 1999-2001, and documents the visit by the Liz Lerman Dance Exchange to the University of Michigan. The visit by this professional dance company was co-sponsored by the Arts of Citizenship Program. Included is a VHS videotape of the public lecture by Liz Lerman on September 29, 1999.
    - Liz Lerman Lecture, Videocassette September 28, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1999-2001 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Press Coverage 1999-2001 (Box 2)
  - Homelands Project
    The Homelands Project (4 folders) contains audio and visual records in addition to correspondence and publicity. In this project, AOC produced dramatic materials from oral histories in the diverse neighborhood of southwest Detroit, The project focused mainly on Detroit's Michigan Central train station. Material includes a lobby exhibit of historic photographs. Audio recordings include two cassette tapes and a VHS videocassette of the May 11, 2002 performance of "Homelands" by the Matrix Theatre Company.
    - Audio recordings (Box 3)
      - "Homelands" Talk, parts 1-2 2004, 2 audiocassettes (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Performance May 11, 2002, VHS tape (Box 3)
    - Publicity 2002-2004 (Box 3)
  - "Paradise Valley Revisited" Project
    The "Paradise Valley Revisited" Project (1 folder) contains the script for a musical play that was performed as part of AOC.
    - Script (Box 3)
  - "Poetry of Everyday Life"
    The "Poetry of Everyday Life" Project (4 folders) contains photographs, press coverage, project and course descriptions, and publicity. Project and course descriptions include a three-page description of the project and syllabi from UC 312 and Honors 251. This project, which lasted from 1998-2003, combined research with poetry and community life for elementary students, partially taught by UM students. Elementary students produced writing and art projects after taking field trips to local areas in Ann Arbor.
    - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Press Coverage 2001 (Box 3)
    - Project and Course Descriptions 1999 undated (Box 3)
    - Publicity 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Radio Documentaries
    The Radio Documentaries Project (8 folders) consists of audio recordings (audio cassettes and compact discs), class schedules, and press coverage. The Radio Documentaries project worked on a number of documentaries with Michigan Public Radio, including research, interviews, and scripts. The audio recordings include cassette tapes and CDs of programs aired on Michigan Public Radio. Recordings include "B-Boys in Detroit," "Future Series with David Scobey," "Listening to Youth," "Out of the Tower" interview with David Scobey, "Passing on Bop," and the award-winning "Riot Diaries" about the Detroit riots. The class schedules include a syllabus for CAAS 487.
    - Audio recordings
      - "B-Boys in Detroit," 2005, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 3)
      - "Future Series with David Scobey", 1 audiocassettes (Box 3)
      - "Listening to Youth,", 2 optical disks CDs (Box 3)
      - "Out of the Tower," 1999, 1 optical disks CDs; 1 audiocassettes (Box 3)
      - "Passing on Bop," 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 3)
      - "Riot Diaries: Coming of Age During the Riot Years," 2001, 1 optical disks CDs; 1 audiocassettes (Box 3)
    - Class Schedule (Box 3)
    - Press Coverage 2002-2005 (Box 3)
  - Students on Site (SOS) -- Ann Arbor
    The Students on Site (SOS) Project was the first major project undertaken by AOC. It served as a model and core project to lunch other collaborations with AOC. SOS is divided into two parts: Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti. Students on Site-Ann Arbor (5 folders) contains group meetings, orientation and training, quarterly reports, and summary materials. The group meetings are broken in two groups, the SOS meeting and workshop notes and staff meeting minutes. Summary materials include an abstract of the project, SOS team members, flyers describing the project, and a master list of partnerships. Students on Site-Ypsilanti (4 folders) contains meeting minutes, project summary, and summary reports. The project summary is a bound copy that describes the project, including the curriculum. The summary report was written for the 2002-2003 academic school year, and includes a calendar, meeting information, lesson plans, and archival resources useful for teaching.
    - SOS Meeting and Workshop Notes 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes 1998 (Box 3)
    - Quarterly Report 1999 (Box 3)
    - Summary Materials 1998-2001 (Box 3)
  - Students on Site (SOS) -- Ypsilanti
    - Meeting Minutes 2003 (Box 3)
    - Orientation and Training Manual 2001 (Box 3)
    - Project Summary (Box 3)
    - Summary Report 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "Telling It" Initiative
    The "Telling It" Initiative (1 folder) was a community-based arts and literacy project which assessed how engaging children ages 7-10 years old in the creative arts can foster growth in writing skills. Materials include notes, correspondence, newspaper articles, grant information, and pamphlets.
    - General 2005 (Box 3)
  - Underground Railroad Project
    The Underground Railroad Project (16 folders) contains administration, bus tour information, and materials related to "Midnight Journey." The project undertook groundbreaking research on the Underground Railroad and African-American community life in nineteenth century Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti. Administration records include minimal correspondence, the 2001 exhibit presentation, expenses, meeting notes and summaries, project toolkit, and reports. The bus tour records include an audio recording of Bill Browning giving the bus tour (cassette tape), 2002 program summary, and the 1999 script from the Bill Browning bus tour. "Midnight Journey," a traveling public exhibit, contains docent guides, press coverage, publicity, slides from the opening reception in 2001 at the Ann Arbor District Library, and website design printouts for a website that may or may not have ever been published.
    - AACHM
      - Program and Event Schedule 2005 (Box 3)
    - Administration
      - Correspondence 1998-2004 (Box 3)
      - Exhibit Presentation December 12, 2001 (Box 3)
      - Expenses (Box 3)
      - Grant Application 4/1/2002 (Box 3)
      - Meeting Notes and Summaries 1998-2002 (Box 3)
      - Project Toolkit 2002 (Box 3)
      - Reports 1999-2003 (Box 3)
    - Bus Tour
      - Audio recording
        - "Bill Browning Bus Tour", 1 audiocassettes (Box 3)
      - Program Summary 2002 (Box 3)
      - Script (Box 3)
    - "Midnight Journey"
      - Docent Guides (Box 3)
      - Press Coverage 1999-2002 (Box 3)
      - Publicity (Box 3)
      - Slides of Exhibit and Opening 2001 (Box 3)
      - Website Design (Box 3)
- AOC Website
  The Website series (163 digital files, 36.3 MB) was captured from a direct transfer from the Arts of Citizenship Program website http://www.artsofcitizenship.umich.edu. The website capture included separate project websites in some cases. Note that some functionality has been lost in the attempt to preserve the website. The captured website contains nine sections: a description of the program, works and resources, information on staff, project information, funding, programs and speakers AOC supports, events, exhibit space, and a "what's new" corner. The Projects web page contains a table of all projects, as well as short descriptions of all projects, sometimes with links to a separate project website (Students on Site, Altar of Democracy, Broadway Park Design, and Listening to Youth). The website contains information not otherwise found in the collection.
  - Website capture July 18, 2005, 163 digital files 36.3 MB